# **RITU PANDE**

Apartment 303 24456 Conifer Farmington Hills, MI, 48335 United States

### **Profile**

Technology principal, specializing in applied cryptography, public key infrastructure and security architecture for connected embedded devices. Experience in technically building and mentoring large teams to take a product/service from conceptualization/pre-sales to production.

Mobile: +1-248-756-9513

I am also an independent researcher, collaborating with experts in academia. My research interests include:

- Graph Neural Networks
- Group Convolutions
- Self-Organizing Systems

For more information please refer <u>ritupande.github.io</u>

# **Research Experience:**

- Publications
  - Hierarchical Neural Cellular Automata, R Pande, D Grattarola Artificial Life Conference (ALife 2023) | Paper, Code, Talk
- Projects
  - Adaptive Traffic Signal Control using Deep Reinforcement Learning. Code
- Skills
  - Tensor Flow, Numpy, Python, Object Oriented Programming
  - Self-organizing systems, Neural Cellular Automata, Deep Learning, Deep Reinforcement Learning, Graph Neural Networks
- Certifications.
  - Natural Language Processing Specialization
  - AI for Medicine
  - Mathematics for Machine Learning
  - Deep Learning Specialization
  - Reinforcement Learning Specialization

### **Professional Experience:**

Employment

Company	Designation	Duration
General Motors	Software Architect, Technology Lead	Oct 2021 – Till date
Capgemini Group/ Altran Group/ Aricent Technologies/ Hughes Software Systems	<ul> <li>Director Technology</li> <li>Principal Systems Engineer</li> <li>Senior Technical Lead</li> <li>Technical Lead</li> <li>Senior Software Engineer</li> </ul>	July 2004 - Oct 2021
Wipro Technologies	Software Engineer	Oct 2002-July 2004
Innodata Information Technologies	System Engineer	Aug 2001 - Sept-2002

### Recent Projects

- General Motors connected car infotainment (2014- Till Date).

### Lead Security Architect responsible for:

- Authoring PKI specification for all connected ECUs capturing procurement, renewal and revocation strategy of device end-entity certificates.
- o Authoring Secured Onboard Communication (SecOC) specification for infotainment ECU.
- Authoring specification for flexible key provisioning for infotainment ECU at plant and assembly.
- Designing strategy for integration of ECU key store with trusted applications in Qualcomm Trusted Execution Environment.
- Designing ECU trusted certificate store strategy.
- Mentoring and training implementation teams on security and applied cryptography fundamentals.
- Leading end-to-end integration of the security features between connected infotainment ECU and the back-end servers.
- o Threat modelling for attack vectors on connected ECUs.

# Lead Power and State Management Architect, responsible for: ( 2014- Till Date)

- o Authoring specification for power and state management for infotainment ECU
- Technically leading implementation teams within General Motors and Tier-I suppliers to implement the power and state management functionality across SoC and Vehicle Interface Processor in infotainment ECU.
- Spearhead triaging and execution
- Nokia Siemens Network(NSN) Femto Access Point (FAP) ( 2013- 2014)

Project Technical lead for the design and execution of security solution in FAP device.

- Designing the Trusted Execution Environment strategy in FAP using ARM Trustzone architecture.
- Technically leading the porting and integration of Aricent developed LTE stacks on SoC vendor's (Broadcom) BSP.
- Designing and leading execution of integration and optimization strategy of ciphering at LTE air interface with SoC provided HW accelerators.
- Leading the integration of encryption in the IPSec layer of Linux kernel with SoC provided HW accelerators.
- Technically leading the design and execution of integration of Strongswan Internet Key Exchange version 2 (IKEv2) stack on Linux operating system with FAP fast path.
- Designing and leading execution of secure boot strategy for FAP
- Leading the execution of strategy for secure over-the-air download and subsequent flashing of firmware.
- Designing the IP filter rules for implementing NATing in the FAP device.
- Nokia Siemens Network (NSN) Flexi-Edge Base Transceiver Station (BTS) (2009-2013)

Feature Lead for design and execution of security and transport solutions for the base station

- Technically leading the design and execution of integration of Strongswan Internet Key Exchange version 2 (IKEv2) stack on QNX operating system with fast path executed in network processor.
- Technically leading the architecture, design and execution of CLM strategy for procurement, renewal and revocation of device end-entity certificates in the BTS

#### Skills

- Security architecture for embedded devices, Applied Cryptography, Public Key Infrastructure, Platform Security, Transport Layer Security, Android Security, Trusted Execution Environment, Secure Programming, Secured Onboard Communication.
- Automotive Network Architecture, Vehicle Power Management, IP Transport, L2/L3 Switching
- Creating technical proposals detailing solutions to customer requirements and effectively presenting them.
- Programming Languages: C, object-oriented Python
- Tools: Jira, Github, Enterprise Architect
- Operation Systems: Linux, QNX
- Standards: X.509, IKEv2, IPsec, TLSv2, SHE, TrustZone
- Excellent verbal and oral communication skills

# **Leadership Experience:**

- Experience in leading technical task force across multiple tier-1 suppliers and OEM teams to bring product features to fruition from their concept inception to deployment.
- Extensive experience in technically building and mentoring large teams (largest team size being 45) in the area of IP transport, security and layer 2 switching and routing strategies.
- Deft at providing technical leadership across parallel projects, resolving interface issues across multiple subsystems.

### **Teaching Experience:**

- Aricent Technologies: Organizational trainer for 'Debugging Skills'.
- General Motors: Organizational trainer for 'Security and Applied Cryptography Fundamentals'.

# **Educational Qualifications:**

Bachelor of Information Tech. (1997-2001) Indraprastha College, Delhi University, India.

### **Awards and Achievements:**

- 1 Certificate of Merit in National Mathematics Olympiad competition, 1995
- 2 Individual Employee Excellence award, Altran Group, 2008

### **Extra-Curricular Achievements:**

- 1. 1st Degree Black Belt holder in ITF Tae-kwon-do
- 2. 1 Gold and 1 Silver in South Asian Tae-kwon-do Championships (ITF), Dec 2008
- 3 2 Gold and 1 Silver in National Tae-kwon-do Championships, Dec 2006
- 4 Completed Airtel Delhi Half Marathon '09 and '10

I hereby agree that the above information is true to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Ritu Pande